<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Povilas Blog (Posts about productivity)</title><link>http://blog.povilasb.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://blog.povilasb.com/categories/productivity.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Dec 2022 18:28:53 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>How I made my own time tracking tool in 1 day</title><link>http://blog.povilasb.com/posts/time-tracker-in-1day/</link><dc:creator>Povilas Balciunas</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I was always interested in how long it takes me to do stuff. Especially when
it comes to programming. It's like sports: you measure how well you perform
and next time you try to do it better. Otherwise there's no point of doing
something, if you're not improving, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I've been attending
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.coursera.org/course/ml"&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt; course. Study load
was estimated 5-7 hours/week. But everytime I was doing the assignments I
felt like I was spending at least twice more than the estimation. Then I
decided I need to measure my activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are lot's of time tracking
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comparison_of_time_tracking_software"&gt;tools&lt;/a&gt;
out there: free, non-free, desktop, mobile, web based, etc. Most of them are
really hard to work with. You have to open a web site or a dialog
box, fill forms, press buttons, etc. It requires me to use my
mouse and do bunch of steps that decreases my performance and interrupts
main tasks. Eventually the motivation to track my time perishes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="the-problem"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best case scenario would be if my computer could automatically monitor my
activities. Well unfortunately, most of the time it's too hard to interpret
human and computer interaction as a higher level task. E.g. computers might
not easily understand that browsing facebook means that I'm still doing my
job - advertising my product. That's why I have to explicitly tell which tasks
I'm working on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal was to reduce the burden of this action - &lt;strong&gt;task tracking&lt;/strong&gt;. I would
like to put as less effort as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="solution"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To achieve my goals I have implemented my own time tracking tool which
integrates into my operating systems environment. It's available on
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/povilasb/awesome-time-tracker"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;. Where you can
find the description how to setup it on your Awesome window manager.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently I'm using Debian OS and
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://awesome.naquadah.org/"&gt;Awesome window manager&lt;/a&gt; on top of it. Awesome
is litteraly awesome. It allows me to forget that I ever needed a mouse :).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="first-attempt"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;First attempt&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting new task is easy. I hit &lt;em&gt;ctrl+windows_key+a&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; stands for
activity), and I get a prompt to enter the new task I'm working on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/awesome_time_tracker_prompt.png" src="http://blog.povilasb.com/images/awesome_time_tracker_prompt.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once i hit &lt;em&gt;ENTER&lt;/em&gt; the task is marked as started. When I hit
&lt;em&gt;ctrl+windows_key+s&lt;/em&gt; the task is stopped. Once task is stopped it is saved
to text file (CSV format). So later I can import my tasks to Excel and plot
some charts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="second-shot"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Second shot&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything is simple and working pretty well. Except for task reports. I hate
to do Excel imports or read the task reports from text file. So eventually
I used &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://qmonix.com"&gt;Qmonix&lt;/a&gt; monitoring and analytics platform.
It provides me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;server that collects my tasks;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;client side libraries to send task data to server;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;and dashboard to visualise and overview my tasks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/qmonix_arch.png" src="http://blog.povilasb.com/images/qmonix_arch.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, it took me 33 minutes to integrate Qmonix to my time tracker.
And after that I was able to get some nice charts without breaking a sweat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="how-did-i-do-it"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How did I do it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all I downloaded Qmonix server from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://qmonix.com"&gt;http://qmonix.com&lt;/a&gt;. The zip archive
has &lt;em&gt;qmonix-qemu.sh&lt;/em&gt; script that runs the server:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;$ ./qmonix-qemu.sh&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the server started I was able to see such window:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/qmonix_vm_running.png" src="http://blog.povilasb.com/images/qmonix_vm_running.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I grabbed Qmonix &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/qmonix/client-lua"&gt;Lua library&lt;/a&gt;.
Because Awesome WM is configurable with Lua. Then I edited my awesome time
tracker to send tasks to Qmonix server rather than save them to text file.
That's it :) - I was able to overview the time I spent on my tasks in Web
browser (&lt;em&gt;http://localhost:8337/dashboard/index.html&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One nice thing is that now I'm able to host the server and send my task time
data from any place: home and work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="example"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, let's come back to the machine learning course. I used this awesome time
tracker to see how much time it actually took me to do my course work.
First of all I separated three different tasks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;wathing videos,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;answering quiz questions,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;and doing programming assignments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I tracked each activity separately:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/awesome_time_tracker_prompt.png" src="http://blog.povilasb.com/images/awesome_time_tracker_prompt.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/awesome_time_tracker_prompt_3.png" src="http://blog.povilasb.com/images/awesome_time_tracker_prompt_3.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/awesome_time_tracker_prompt_2.png" src="http://blog.povilasb.com/images/awesome_time_tracker_prompt_2.png"&gt;
&lt;section id="time-report-review"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Time report review&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's time to take a look how much time I spent on machine learning during a
single week. Let's revise that estimated course load was 5-7 hours/week, but
I felt like I was spending way more time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's see the total time spent on machine learning. I will create column chart
that displays time spent on machine learning daily:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/qmonix_query.png" src="http://blog.povilasb.com/images/qmonix_query.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result I get such chart:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/qmonix_column_chart.png" src="http://blog.povilasb.com/images/qmonix_column_chart.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What it says it, that on march 1st I spent 10 000 seconds studying machine
learning. Which is about 2.7 hours. So it's twice better than the estimated
time :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I wanted to see how much time each subtask (videos, quiz, programming)
took separately:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/qmonix_query_grouping_operator.png" src="http://blog.povilasb.com/images/qmonix_query_grouping_operator.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/qmonix_pie_chart.png" src="http://blog.povilasb.com/images/qmonix_pie_chart.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the time I spent on watching videos. Although, I expected to see that
programming tasks are the most time consuming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also I measured my breaks. Which later I compared to the machine learning
course work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/qmonix_settings_work_vs_break.png" src="http://blog.povilasb.com/images/qmonix_settings_work_vs_break.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/qmonix_work_vs_break.png" src="http://blog.povilasb.com/images/qmonix_work_vs_break.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it was obvious why it felt like it was taking too much time. I spent more
time on breaks than working on my tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="to-sum-up"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;To sum up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously I need to work on my concentration :).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>dyi</category><category>productivity</category><guid>http://blog.povilasb.com/posts/time-tracker-in-1day/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2014 14:49:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>